<doc>
  <page id="main">
    <h>Map of the Spanish Florida Missions</h>
    <p>This map is part of an ongoing project to locate the Spanish-period Florida
      misssions in relation to sites from the 18th and 19th centuries. It deals
      mostly with roads and trails and the places that these connect.  This map is
      a work in progress.</p>

    <linkcol>
      <link ref="roads">Guide to roads on map</link><br/>
      <link ref="omiss">Overview of mission system</link><br/>
    </linkcol>
    <linkcol>
      <link ref="project">Notes on this project</link><br/>
      <link ref="privacy">Privacy Policy</link><br/>
    </linkcol>
  </page>

  <page id="roads">
    <h>Guide to roads on map</h>
    <p>No one among the early Spanish, whether explorers, soldiers, priests, or
      colonists, left us maps of the mission routes.  We do know that they followed
      trails that the native people had already made and that later roads followed
      these paths—more or less.</p>
    <dl>
      <dt><i>El Camino Reál</i></dt>
      <dd>This was the main east-west route from St. Augustine to the Apalachee
        province during the Spanish period.  Scant direct evidence of this route
        remains today, but much of it may be inferred from more recent roads.  The
        route of Bellamy Road, much of which quite evident today, indicates the
        general route of <i>El Camino Reál</i>, but may not be completely accurate.
        Joseph Purcell's map, made 50 years before Bellamy Road, showed routes the
        British used during their time in Florida.  In many places this it seems to
        follow the Spanish routes more accurately than does Bellamy Road, but this
        map has its own problems, as noted below.</dd>

      <dt>Bellamy Road / Federal Road (marked in color <strip color="#22AA22"/>)</dt>
      <dd>Authorized in 1824, this was the first Federal road project in the new
        Florida territory. It ran from Pensacola to St. Augustine via Ft. St. Louis
        (San Luís de Talimali) in what is now Tallahassee.  It would appear to be a
        good proxy for <i>El Camino Reál</i> since the 1824 law specifed that it
        follow the Spanish routes as nearly as possible.  The road's project
        manager, Captain John Burch, reported that he followed the Spanish route
        pretty closely.  Many fragments of this road survive today as evidenced by
        names like Bellamy Road (for the contractor responsible for more than half
        the route), St. Augustine Road, or Federal Road.  The difficulty is that
        the old trails would likely have meandered much more than these modern
        roads do.  Was it Captain Burch who made them straight, or did others do
        so in the 200 intervening years?  Also, Bellamy Road made a notable
        divergence from the Spanish route to pass through the settlement that
        would become Newnansville, seat of Alachua County; there may be other such
        excursions, such as detours to avoid seasonally flooded areas of San Pedro
        Bay.  In any event, Bellamy Road may not be our best proxy for <i>El Camino
        Reál</i>.
        <p>In many places Bellamy Road has disappeared from the landscape.  One of
          these places, ironically, is at Newnansville, where only the old cemetery
          remains.  Sometimes old maps reveal the path of Bellamy Road, as do old
          plat maps of Newnansville.  Other old maps, such as Henry Tanner's 1833
          map, are also of help, if with less detail.</p>
        <p>The trace of Bellamy Road as shown on the main map is incomplete:  it
          runs only between Tallahassee and Newnansville.  This is because the
          route becomes more speculative beyond these endpoints.  There are two
          limiting factors toward the west: 1. <i>El Camino Reál</i> probably did
          not extend beyond San Luís mission and 2. Bellamy's contribution to the
          Federal Road was only east of the Ocklockonee River.</p>
      </dd>

      <dt>Stuart-Purcell Route (marked in color <strip color="#992299"/>)</dt>
      <dd>The British, though ruling Florida only 20 years, made several important
       explorations of the territory.  One was by the surveyor Joseph Purcell, who
       prepared <i>A Map of the Road from Pensacola to St. Augustine</i>.  This
       map, of which the 8½-foot wide original is in London, depicts what may be a
       more true representation of <i>El Camino Reál</i> than does Bellamy Road
       (Boyd, 1938).  I digitized this map and encountered several problems.  The
       projection onto the flat sheet of paper does not reflect the curvature of
       the earth, which is considerable over the map's 5.9 degrees of latitude.
       It also appears that the dead reckoning he appears to have used had little
       correction for accumulated error.  These problems led me to have to stretch
       the very large raster of the Stuart-Purcell map to make it align with
       well-known locations such as San Luís mission, Charles Ferry, Ichetucknee,
       and Lake Santa Fé. The greatest problem, however, is that west of Potohiriba
       in central Madison County the British did not use roads that followed the
       old <i>Camino Reál</i>.  In this part of the state, it appears better to
       stick with the Bellamy Road.<br/>
       <p>The road in the Stuart-Purcell map splits in three places into a
         northerly and a southerly route.  In all three places the cartographer
         distinguished between the main and the alternate route.</p>
       <p>The road on the British map runs within a mile of Bellamy Road for most
         of the way east of the Suwannee.  In modern Madison and Jefferson counties
         the roads are separated by up to eight miles.  It is evident that the two
         later roads followed different primorial paths.  The British followed
         paths the Seminoles and Miccosukee used—and likely avoided those they did
         not.  John Lee Williams, in his 1837 book <i>A View of West Florida</i>,
         wrote this about the route near Tallahassee when he explored there in
         1823: "At a little south-east of the town...the Indian paths cross this
         great road [but] never follow it, with almost a religious caution."
         (p. 33)  The southerly branch of Stuart-Purcell's road runs east of
         Tallahassee around the north of Lake Lafayette, whereas Bellamy Road ran
         south of the lake as per Williams' description.  It appears Bellamy Road
         is correct in this region.</p>
      </dd>

      <dt>Other mission routes (marked in color <strip color="#BB33AA"/>)</dt>
      <dd>Some roads are known or supposed to have existed in mission times, such
        as what Kenneth Johnson in is 1991 disseration calls the Santa Fe Trail,
        named for the Santa Fé de Toloca mission along it.  Other trails marked in
        this color serve only to connect mission sites with nearby roads.  Some of
        these are quite speculative.
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <h2>Line thickness and hatching indicate degree of certainty</h2>
    <p>The thicker and more solid the map trace, the greater degree of confidence.
      In places where a line on the map is solid and wide, the route in that place
      is well attested and is still evident in the modern environment.  The source
      dataset contains indications of types and number of attestations and road
      conditions for each route.  <i>Misiones</i>, the program which processes the
      source dataset into a form suitable for display on the map, weighs these
      factors to determine how each line is presented.</p>
  </page>

  <page id="omiss">
    <h>Overview of the Spanish Missions</h>
    <p>The earliest Spanish explorers in Florida concentrated on the southern
      Gulf coast, where they clashed with the native Calusa.  Conflict was
      inevitable:  these explorers were famously zealous of conquest, glory, and
      riches, while the Calusa, calling themselves the 'fierce people', exacted
      tribute from all the other tribes of south Florida. The Spanish had very
      little to show for their efforts in South Florida.</p>
    <p>The expeditions of Panfilo de Narváez (1528) and Hernándo de Soto (1539)
      both avoided Calusa territory but failed in their goal of finding fabled
      riches in the middle of the continent.  The brutality of their tactics,
      however, served to engender hostility against the Spanish that lasted
      decades—even among peoples who might otherwise have been more kindly
      disposed to the Europeans.  This frustrated Spanish settlement and
      missionary efforts all the way up the peninsula and across the panhandle.
      The idealistic missionary Luís Cáncer, for example, went in peace in 1549
      to the Tocobaga at Tampa Bay but was killed on the spot.</p>
    <p>The place where the Spanish finally had success was the part of Florida that
      they had ignored and, ironically enough, might have continued to ignore if it
      weren't for the arrival of the French in that region.  French Hugenots made a
      settlement on the St. John's River they called Fort Caroline.  The natives in
      this area were the Saturiwa, part of the Mocama chiefdom, which was one of the
      many chiefdoms of the Timucua people.  The Timucua ranged over a very large
      area in north Florida and south Georgia and shared a common culture and
      language, yet, unlike the Calusa, had no centralized organization.  They were
      also much less war-like and, crucially, more likely to cooperate with the
      Europeans.</p>
    <p>Alarmed by the encroachment of the French, the Spanish king sent Pedro
      Menéndez de Avilés to Florida to expel the French and set up an outpost to
      protect Spanish interests.  Menéndez did so in short order and took up his
      position as the governor of Florida.  Franciscan missionaries soon went forth
      to visit many of the Timucua chiefdoms.  This became the first step in closer
      relations with chiefdoms to the north of St. Augustine and into the interior
      of north Florida.</p>
    <p>In contrast to the earlier failed attempt to set up a colony at Pensacola
      Bay, St. Augustine, with the support of the natives in its hinterlands, was
      able to produce the food needed to sustain itself and export beef and corn.
      Keeping up this business was one of the greatest concerns of the Spanish in
      their whole time in Florida.</p>
    <p>The missionaries and the soldiers and farmers that followed them used the
      trail network that the natives had used for centuries before them.  The most
      important of these ran straight west from St. Augustine and continued all the
      way to the town of Anhaica, in what is now Tallahassee.  We know this route
      by the name <i>El Camino Reál</i>, the Royal Road, even though the Spanish
      did not start using this name until the late 17th century.</p>
    <p>The Spanish economic system in the New World depended heavily on the labor
      of its native peoples.  The earliest labor system, the <i>encomienda</i>, was
      especially harsh to peoples such as the Aztec and Inca.  A series of laws,
      particularly the <i>Leyes Nuevas</i> (New Laws) of 1542, greatly curtailed
      the use of the <i>encomienda</i>, forbade many abuses, and granted the
      Indians many rights.  Though not completely observed, these reforms did make
      the lives of the natives of Florida much better than they could have been.
      Native labor in Florida normally ran on two levels:  farming or animal
      husbandry in the hinterlands and direct labor in construction or the portage
      of goods.  The latter type put more of a strain on the individual laborer:
      not only was he absent from village and family during his two years of
      labor service, but the work was strenuous enough to damage the health.</p>
    <p>More devastating was a force that neither the Europeans nor the Americans
      understood:  exposure to novel diseases like measles, smallpox, whooping
      cough, chicken pox, and the plague.  Between overwork and disease the native
      population declined steadily through the whole mission period.  The effect
      for any given region was correlated to the length of time the Spanish had
      dealings with it.</p>
    <p>These population declines caused a loss of productivity that motivated the
      Spanish to expand ever westward.  In all cases the missionaries went first.
      Fr. Baltasár López visited Ayacuto at Ichetucknee Springs a decade before the
      Spanish established there, and Fr. Martín Prieto went to Ivitachuco a full 25
      years before the colonization reached that Apalachee town.  The missionaries
      often remarked on the fervor they often found among the Timucua and
      Apalachee toward the Christian religion.  At various times the Timucua
      uprose against the Spanish, but in most of these instances they never harmed
      the priests.</p>
    <p>Eventually the Spanish missions continued past the Aucilla River, the
      western edge of the Timucuans, and spread into the Apalachee lands.  The
      Apalachee were rather different than the Timucuans:  their government was
      much more hierarchical, the population density was much higher, their
      agriculture was more efficient, and their ways were more violent.  Even
      though de Soto had spent the whole winter in Anhaica, the Spanish worked
      well with them.  Here they established the largest mission in the whole
      system, complete with a fort:  San Lúis de Talimali, also known as San
      Luís de Apalache.</p>
    <p>The Spanish mission system did not extend far beyond the Apalachee
      territory, which itself covered only two modern counties (Leon and
      Jefferson).  In 1702 the English Col. Charles Moore began his attacks on the
      Spanish Florida.  The English and their Yamasee, Creek, and other Indian
      allies overwhelmed the Spanish and destroyed their missions.  Even the
      defensible San Lúis and Ivitachuco could not long hold out; the inhabitants
      either fled eastward to St. Augustine or joined the invaders.  Interestingly,
      the very last mission to hold out in the interior of Florida had been the
      first to be established.  The defenders of San Francisco de Potano finally
      fled to St. Augustine in 1706.  St. Augustine itself never fell to British
      arms; the city and its Castillo went over to Britain only as a result of the
      1763 Treaty of Paris that ended the French and Indian War.  At that time, the
      inhabitants of St. Augustine, including all the remaining Timucua, evacuated
      to Havana.</p>
  </page>

  <page id="project">
    <h>Overview of the project</h>
    <p>This project began with a request that I look into the location a Spanish
      called <i>Aspalaga</i> that was at or near the site of a 19th-century
      plantation in Jefferson County with a Spanish name, <i>El Destino</i>.  This
      intrigued me not only because I had an interest in Spanish missions, but also
      because the plantation appeared to be near Bellamy Road.  Indeed, I found
      that the plantation straddled the road for some miles and that there were a
      couple of likely nearby locations for the San Juan de Aspalaga mission.</p>
    <p>I also found that it was possible to guage the location of long-disappeared
      missions based on their distances from other missions described in the
      contemporaneous descriptions of them.  I wanted to place these on the map for
      two reasons:  to visualize where the were in relation to the others and to
      measure the distances between them on routes that connected them.</p>
    <p>I saw the map as a way to visualize the missions in relation to one another
      as a help into further research.  I have made successive refinements to the
      map over time and will continue to do so as my research proceeds.</p>
    <p>A large portion of the work has centered around digitizing historical maps
      to capture the paths they trace as series of points that consist of
      latitude/longitude pairs.  A similar approach works to trace the paths of
      routes that are still visible today.  This can even take the form of tracing
      the points collected from a GPS receiver while traversing a path.  For
      tracing maps, whether historic or modern, my tool of choice is the
      open-source program QGIS.  Whatever the source, the next requirement was to
      put all the collected map-trace data into a common format.  I designed a
      custom format paired with a program that consumes this map data and generates
      a JSON (Javascript Object Notation) file that the map application can load
      into the browser.</p>
    <p>The map-display application via which you view the map and read this page
      has its source code at <a href="https://github.com/potano/elDestino">
      https://github.com/potano/elDestino</a>.  It uses the Leaflet JS library
      (<a href="https://leafletjs.com">https://leafletjs.com</a>) to display the
      map.  The source code for the dataset-processing program, called <i>misiones</i>,
      is at <a href="https://github.com/potano/misiones"
      >https://github.com/potano/misiones</a>.</p>
      <p>—Mike Thompson</p>
  </page>

  <page id="privacy">
    <h>Privacy policy</h>
    <p>This application collects no personally identifiable information nor does it
      transmit any information to the server beyond what is part of a standard HTTP
      request.  This application does not use cookies.</p>
    <p>A planned future enhancement to the program will record the most recently
      viewed map position plus limited configuration information via your browser's
      web-storage mechanism.  None of this information will be transmitted to the
      server.</p>
    <p>The source code for this Javascript application, the source dataset, and the
      build script are available for your inspection on GitHub:
      <a href="https://github.com/potano/elDestino">https://github.com/potano/elDestino</a>
    </p>
    <p>The source code for the application that processes the source dataset into a
      form that that Javascript application can use is also at GitHub:
      <a href="https://github.com/potano/misiones">https://github.com/potano/misiones</a>
    </p>
  </page>
</doc>

